Register of the Thomas Ray Bodine Papers, 1941-1982
Hoover Institution Archives
Thomas Ray Bodine Papers,
1941-1982
82035
Bodine, Thomas Ray, 1915-
11 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 3 envelopes (5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, notes, memoranda, reports, newsletters, printed matter, and photographs, relating to relocation of Japanese Americans during World War II, and to the placement of Japanese-American students in colleges.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Education.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; United States.
Biographical Note
On December 7, 1941, when the Japanese attacked Pearl Harbor, Thomas R. Bodine was in training for foreign service with the American Friends Service Committee. As a result, rather than being sent overseas, he was assigned to Seattle, Washington, to aid the Japanese-American population on the West Coast. He arrived in late January, several weeks before President Roosevelt issued Executive Order 9066 (Feb. 19, 1942). During the months of January and February, the Seattle Friends Committee (as well as other West Coast Friends committees) was active in helping Japanese-Americans relocate voluntarily to the interior of the country, and performed an important role in advising and informing the Japanese-American population about the events which culminated in the order of March 2, 1942, excluding all persons of Japanese ancestry from the area.
Through the spring and early summer, as Japanese-Americans were collected in assembly centers and subsequently transferred to more permanent relocation centers, the Friends Committees provided many important services such as preparation for evacuation, transportation, provision of food and supplies, and agitation for improvement of camp conditions. Even before internment was an established fact, efforts of religious, educational and other service organizations focused on relocation of individuals from the camps. The attempt to relocate college students was formalized on May 29 1942, with the establishment of the National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council (NJASRC). In June, Thomas Bodine went from Seattle to the West Coast office of the NJASRC, located in Berkeley, which had been set up to deal with the logistical arrangements for student relocation. In December, 1942, following internal administrative problems, he became the West Coast Director. In February of 1943, the decision was made to centralize the program in Philadelphia to allow closer contact with the War Relocation Authority, as well as educational institutions and cooperating service organizations on the East Coast. At that time, Thomas Bodine became the NJASRC Field Director, traveling to the various relocation centers as the liaison between counselors and students and the main office. He continued in this position until 1945, when he was reassigned to duty overseas in France.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, notes, memoranda, reports, newsletters, printed matter, and photographs, relating to relocation of Japanese Americans during World War II, and to the placement of Japanese-American students in colleges.
Container List
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1942-1982. (Box 1)
  Drafts, notes, clippings, correspondence, transcripts, printed copies, arranged chronologically.
  - Speech notes (mostly handwritten, some typed notes and transcripts) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Published Material
    - Correspondence (regarding publications) (Folder 2)
    - Articles
      - Japanese Evacuation, AFSERCO News Vol. 2, 1942 June. (Folder 3)
      - The Japanese Displacement, Friends Intelligencer, 1942 June 6. Includes drafts. (Folder 4)
      - For Reasons of Military Necessity, Alumni Record, Germantown Friends School, 1943 April 15. Includes drafts. (Folder 5)
      - From Camp to College, 1944. National Japanese Student Relocation Council pamphlet. Includes drafts. (Folder 6)
  - Holograph of projected book, 1982 (Folder 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1941-1981. (Box 1-2)
  Personal correspondence with friends and family. Arranged chronologically.
  - General (Box 1)
    - n.d. (Folder 8)
    - 1941 Dec.-1942 April
    - 1942 May-July (Folder 9)
    - 1942 Aug.-1943 Jan. (Folder 10)
    - 1943 Feb.-Oct. (Folder 11)
    - 1943 Nov.-1945; 1981 (Folder 12)
  - Family (includes many picture postcards and trip itineraries) (Box 2)
    - 1942 Jan. (Folder 1)
    - 1942 Feb.-April (Folder 2)
    - 1942 May-July (Folder 3)
    - 1942 Aug.-Oct. (Folder 4)
    - 1942 Nov.-Dec. (Folder 5)
    - 1943 Jan.-Feb. (Folder 6)
    - 1943 March-1944 June (Folder 7)
    - 1944 Nov.-1945 Jan. (Folder 8)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1941-1982. (Box 2-10)
  Pamphlets, newspaper clippings, leaflets, bulletins, newsletters, agency reports, manuscripts and miscellany, relating predominately to the issue of Japanese-American displacement during World War II. Includes extensive materials of the National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Japanese-American displacement during World War II (Box 2)
    - General
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Gordon Hirabayashi case (Folder 10)
        - Correspondence
        - Newsletter reports (Pacific Cable)
        - Notes
      - Printed material
        - Pamphlets and brochures (Folder 11-12)
        - Clippings (Folder 13)
      - Non-printed material (Folder 14)
    - Evacuation, 1942 (Box 3)
      - General
      - Printed material (Folder 1)
        - U.S. House of Representatives, Select Committee Investigating National Defense Migration (John H. Tolan, Chairman)
          - Part 29, San Francisco hearings (Folder 2)
          - Part 30, Portland and Seattle hearings (Folder 3)
          - Part 31, Los Angeles and San Francisco hearings (Folder 4)
      - Non-printed material (Folder 5)
        - General
        - American Friends Service Committee
          - General
          - Evacuation bulletins
          - Evacuation reports
    - Internment, 1942-1945
      - General (Folder 6)
      - Printed material (Folder 7)
      - Non-printed material
        - General
        - Camp publications
          - General (Folder 8)
          - Granada, Amache, Colorado
          - Heart Mountain, Heart Mountain, Wyoming
          - Minidoka, Hunt, Idaho (Folder 9)
          - Rohwer, McGehee, Arkansas
          - Topaz (Central Utah), Topaz, Utah (Folder 10)
        - Government publications (Box 4)
          - War Relocation Authority
            - General (Folder 1)
            - Annotated Bibliographies (Folder 2)
            - Community Analysis Reports
            - Project Analysis Series (Folder 3)
            - Press Releases
          - Wartime Civil Control Commission
    - Relocation and resettlement, 1943-1945
      - General
        - General
          - General (Folder 4)
          - Printed material
          - Non-printed material
            - General
            - War Relocation Authority
              - General
              - Handbook Inserts
              - Post-Exclusion Bulletins
        - American Friends Service Committee
          - General (Folder 5)
          - Correspondence
            - 1942 March-June
            - 1942 July-1945 March (Folder 6)
          - Printed material (Folder 7)
          - Non-printed material
      - Student relocation (National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council)
        - General (Folder 8)
          - General
            - General
            - O'Brien, Robert. Typescript copies of chapters from O'Brien, Robert and Roger Daniels, The College Nisei, Salem, NH: Arno Co., 1979 (reprinted from 1949 edition). (Folder 9)
              Includes notes and correspondence.
              - #4: The Fateful Decisions
              - #5: The Tolan Hearings
              - #7: The NJASR Council
              - #10: Wartime Supreme Court Decisions
            - Parkville, Missouri. Case study of community reaction to relocated students. (Box 5, Folder 1)
          - Printed material (Folder 2)
          - Non-printed material
            - Bulletins, 1942
            - Newssheets, 1945 (Folder 3)
        - Correspondence, General
          - General, 1942 Oct.-1982 March (Folder 4)
          - Cooperating Organizations
            - General (Folder 5)
            - Columbia Foundation (Mrs. Charles DeYoung (Marjorie) Elkus)
            - Young Men's/Women's Christian Associations (Folder 6)
          - Individuals (Folder 7)
            - Barnett, Arthur G.
            - Buck, Pearl S.
            - Carr, Ralph L.
            - Keller, Helen
            - Niles, Emory H.
            - Roosevelt, Eleanor
            - Van Der Rohe, Mies
          - Relocation Centers
            - General (includes system-wide mailings) (Folder 8)
            - Newsletters
            - Projects
              - Adrian Farm Labor, Nyssa, Oregon (Folder 9)
              - Colorado River, Poston, Arizona (Folder 10)
              - Gila River, Rivers, Arizona (Folder 11)
              - Granada, Amache, Colorado (Folder 12)
              - Heart Mountain, Heart Mountain, Wyoming (Folder 13)
              - Jerome, Denson, Arkansas (Folder 14)
              - Manzanar, Manzanar, California (Folder 15)
              - Minidoka, Hunt, Idaho (Folder 16)
              - Rohwer, McGehee, Arkansas (Folder 17)
              - Topaz (Central Utah), Topaz, Utah (Folder 18)
              - Tule Lake, Newell, California (Folder 19)
          - U.S. Government Agencies (Folder 20)
            - General
              - General
              - State Department, Joseph C. Grew
            - War Relocation Agency
              - General
              - Office of the Director, Dillon S. Myer
              - Community Analysis Section
              - Community Management Division
              - Reports and Publications
                - Division
          - Universities (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence, Internal (SEE ALSO: Japanese-American Displacement/Relocation and resettlement/General/American Friends Service Committee/Correspondence)
          - 1942 May-Dec. (Folder 2)
          - 1943 Jan.-April (Folder 3)
          - 1943 May (Folder 4)
          - 1943 June-July (Folder 5)
          - 1943 August (Folder 6)
          - 1943 Sept.-Oct. (Folder 7)
          - 1943 Nov.-Dec. (Folder 8)
          - 1944 Jan.-Feb. (Folder 9)
          - 1944 March-April (Folder 10)
          - 1944 May-July (Box 7, Folder 1)
          - 1944 Aug.-Oct. (Folder 2)
          - 1944 Nov.-Dec. (Folder 3)
          - 1945 Jan.-Sept. (Folder 4)
        - Correspondence, Student
          - General (includes form letters) (Folder 5)
          - Representative case study (Folder 6)
          - Selected letters (selected by Thomas R. Bodine as source materials for proposed book)
            - 1942 April-Sept. (Folder 7)
            - 1942 Oct. (Folder 8)
            - 1942 Nov.-Dec. (Folder 9)
            - 1943 Jan. (Folder 10)
            - 1943 Feb. (Folder 11)
            - 1943 March (Folder 12)
            - 1943 April (Folder 13)
            - 1943 May (Folder 14)
            - 1943 June (Folder 15)
            - 1943 July-Sept. (Folder 16)
            - 1943 Oct.-Dec. (Folder 17)
            - 1944 (Folder 18)
            - 1945-1946 (Folder 19)
          - Specially Selected Letters (used as source material by Thomas R. Bodine for his talks) (Box 8, Folder 1)
          - Other student letters (Folder 2, 3)
        - Materials and Procedures
          - Forms (Folder 4)
          - Lists of schools (Folder 5, 6)
          - Notes (Folder 7)
          - Procedures (Folder 8)
          - Student security clearances (Folder 9)
            - Typical dossier memos
            - Rejections
        - Itineraries for Thomas R. Bodine, Field Director, NJASRC (Folder 10)
        - Minutes of Meetings (Folder 11)
        - Notes
          - Administrative (Folder 12)
          - On NJASRC files in Hoover Archives (made by Thomas R. Bodine in 1981) (Folder 13)
        - Reports (Box 9)
          - Field reports (Folder 1)
          - Financial reports (Folder 2)
          - Meeting reports (Folder 3)
          - Progress reports (Folder 4)
    - Post-war relief and reparations, 1947-1982
      - Printed material
        - Clippings (Folder 5)
        - U.S. Department of the Interior, People in Motion, 1947 (Folder 6)
      - Non-printed material
  - Japanese-Canadians, 1944-1957 (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence (case study)
    - Printed material
  - Military service, 1941-1945
    - Conscientious objectors
      - General. Civilian Public Service Corps (American Friends Service Committee) (Folder 8)
      - Correspondence regarding Thomas Bodine's status
        - Registering as C.O., 1941 (Folder 9)
        - Classified as 2-A, 1942 (Folder 10)
        - 2-A classification continued, 1943 (Folder 11)
        - 2-A classification challenged, 1944 (Folder 12)
        - Reclassification as 4-E, returned to 2-A, 1945 (Folder 13)
      - Printed material (Folder 14)
      - Non-printed material (Folder 15)
        - General
        - Absolutist War Objectors Association, The Absolutist, 1943 Oct.-1944 March. Newsletter.
    - Japanese-Americans (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Quakers--policies and activities, 1942-1945
    - General (Folder 2)
    - American Friends Service Committee
      - General
        - General (Folder 3)
        - Correspondence
        - Printed Material (Folder 4)
        - Non-printed Material
          - Bulletins
          - Newsletters
          - Meeting Minutes
      - Civilian Public Service Corps (SEE: Military service/Conscientious objectors/General/CPS)
      - Japanese-American relocation (SEE: Japanese-American displacement/Evacuation/Non-printed material/AFSC; ALSO: Japanese-American displacement/Relocation and resettlement/General/AFSC)
  - U.S. House of Representatives, Un-American Activities Committee (Martin Dies, Chairman), 1943
    - General (Folder 5)
    - Eberharter, Herman P. (Member, Costello subcommittee) Dissenting statement on subcommittee findings and conclusions, 1943
    - War Relocation Authority
      - Comments on press reports of testimony, 1943 May-June
      - Statement on testimony of Harold H. Townsend before Costello subcommittee on May 26, 1943. 1943 July 7
- NOTEBOOK FILE, 1941-1947. (Box 10-11)
  Small pocket notebooks containing information about Thomas Bodine's work with the American Friends Service Committee and the National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council. Includes summary notes by T.R. Bodine. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1941 Dec.-1942 April (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 1942 May-July (Folder 7)
  - 1942 Aug.-Dec. (Folder 8)
  - 1943 Jan.-May (Folder 9)
  - 1943 June-Dec. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1943 Feb.-Aug. (Folder 2)
  - 1944 Sept.-1947 Jan. (Folder 3)
- OVERSIZE FILE, n.d.
  - 1 poster stating West Coast evacuation measures (Box 12)
  - 1 banner announcing relocation center visit of Thomas Bodine
  - 1 art print by unidentified artist
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, c. 1941-1946.
  - 1 print of adult education class at Manzanar relocation center (by Dorothea Lange); 7 prints of Poston or Gila River relocation center; 7 prints of Puyallup evacuation camp (6 duplicates); 3 prints of Thomas Bodine with colleagues; 1 print of unidentified Japanese-American students, 1941-1946 (Folder A)
  - 4 mounted prints (one by Dorothea Lange) of relocation centers, 1942-1943 (Folder mB)
  - 6 prints (one by Dorothea Lange)of relocation centers, 1942-1944 (Folder mC)